Adolf Bolm Papers
Adolf Bolm Papers
1884-1951
Bolm, Adolph, 1884-1951.
5 linear ft.
Correspondence, some in French and Russian, telegrams, scrapbooks, photograph albums, costume sketches, and other materials relating to the San Francisco Ballet, Sergei Diaghilev's Ballet Russe, and others. Correspondents include Agnes De Mille, Romola Nijinsky, Ruth Page, Leopold Stokowski, Igor Stravinsky, and others.
148858
Biographical History
Adolf (also spelled Adolph) Bolm was born in 1884 in St. Petersburg, Russia. At the age of 16 he was accepted by Russia's famed Maryinsky Theatre where he attended school with Anna Pavlova and organized her first tour outside of Russia, dancing as her partner. He danced with the Ballet Russes for several years, working with Diaghilev and Nijinsky. He met his wife Beatrice (Beate) while on tour in Belgium and in 1916 the couple moved to the United States. A son, Olaf A. Bolm, was born on July 4, 1920. By 1926 he had opened a school in Chicago, and went on to work with the St. Louis Municipal Opera, the San Francisco Opera Ballet, the Chicago Lyrical Ballet, and Ballet Theatre in New York, among others. Over the course of his career Bolm was a dancer, choreographer, director, ballet tour organizer and teacher. He also mentored a number of well-known figures in the dance world including Ann Barzel, Syd (Cyd) Charisse, Janet Collins, Constance Finch, Marcia Gibson, Lester Horton, David Lober, Ruth Page, Rosalind Shaffer-deMille, and Ruth Syndon-Jenkins. He was one of five choreographers involved in the founding season for Ballet Theatre in New York. Bolm died in 1951.
[Some information drawn from the Library of Congress Information Bulletin "Wandering Dancer," by Cyrus Parker-Jeanette, February 2005.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Adolf Bolm Papers includes correspondence, photographs, printed material, memorabilia, and writings. Several sound recordings have been transferred to the Belfer Audio Archives (see Related Material below).
Correspondents include George Balanchine, Nadia Boulanger, Colette, Carlos Chavez, Agnes deMille, Sol Hurok, Romola Nijinsky, Max Reinhardt, Leopold Stokowski and Igor Stravinsky. Photographs include pictures of the Adolf Bolm Ballet, Chicago Civic Opera, Diaghilev Ballet and others, as well as some shots of stage sets. Printed material encompasses dance programs, plays, press releases, radio interviews, and reviews. Writings are by Bolm and include some of his own notes. Miscellaneous memorabilia includes books, a piano roll, and scrapbooks. Audiovisual materials inlcudes 16mm films and phonograph records.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical. Within correspondence, material in individual folders is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Dance and theatre; Bolm, Adolph, 1884-1951.; De Mille, Agnes.; Nijinsky, Romola de Pulszky.; Page, Ruth, 1899-1991.; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977.; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971.; Ballets russes.; San Francisco Ballet.; Ballet.; Ballet companies.; Ballet dancers.; Ballets -- Photographs.; Choreographers.; Correspondence.; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Silent films.; Phonograph records.; Ballet dancers.; Choreographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Audiovisual material
  - Films
    - Bach Prelude film (dance performance), bolm_01; 16mm film, 100 feet; Film is damaged and in two parts.
    - Dance Macabre film (dance performance), bolm_02; 16 mm film, 400 feet
  - Phonograph records
    - Adolph Bolm interviewed by Irving Deakin: “What is Russian Ballet” on WQXR (Parts 2 and 4), 15 Apr 1937; bolm_03; 1 aluminum record
    - Adolph Bolm interviewed by Irving Deakin: “What is Russian Ballet” on WQXR (Parts 1 and 3), 15 Apr 1937; bolm_04; 1 aluminum record
    - Bach Cycle No. 1 on WQXR (Part 1 and 2), 08 Apr 1937; bolm_10; 1 aluminum record
    - Bach Cycle No. 1 on WQXR (Part 3 and 4), 08 Apr 1937; bolm_09; 1 aluminum record
    - Bach Cycle No. 1 on WQXR (Parts 5 and 6), 08 Apr 1937; bolm_08; 1 aluminum record
    - Bach Cycle No. 1 on WQXR (Part 7), 08 Apr 1937; bolm_07; 1 aluminum record
    - Bach Cycle No. 1 on WQXR (Part 9), 08 Apr 1937; bolm_06; 1 aluminum record
    - Behind the Scenes at the Russian Ballet (Parts 1 and 6), undated; bolm_05; 1 aluminum record
    - Behind The Scenes At the Russian Ballet (Part 2 and 7), undated; bolm_11; 1 aluminum record
    - Behind the Scenes at the Russian Ballet (Parts 3 and 8), undated; bolm_12; 1 aluminum record
    - Behind The Scenes At the Russian Ballet (Parts 4 and 9), undated; bolm_13; 1 aluminum record
    - Behind the Scenes at the Russian Ballet (Parts 5 and 10), undated; bolm_14; 1 aluminum record
    - Performances, undated; bolm_16; 1 shellac disc
    - [unlabeled shellac disc], undated; bolm_15; 1 shellac disc
    - [unlabeled shellac disc], undated; bolm_17; 1 shellac disc
- Biographical material
  - Correspondence
    - Armitage, Merle (Box 1)
    - Balanchine, George (Box 1)
    - Beaumont, Cyril W. (Box 1)
    - Berman, Eugene (Box 1)
    - Bolm family (Box 1)
    - Bolm, Adolf, telegrams (Box 1)
    - Boulanger, Nadia (Box 1)
    - Calder, Alexander, 24 Nov 1939 (Box 1)
    - Cate, Curtis (Box 1)
    - Chase, Lucia (Box 1)
    - Chavez, Carlos (Box 1)
    - Colette (Box 1)
    - Deakin, Irving (Box 1)
    - DeMille, Agnes (Box 1)
    - Denham, Sergei Ivanovich (Box 1)
    - Escudero, Vicente (Box 1)
    - '47, the Magazine of the Year (Clifton Fadiman) (Box 1)
    - Hurok, Sol (Box 1)
    - Library of Congress (Box 1)
    - Livingston, D.D. (Box 1)
    - National Association of Dance and Affiliated Artists, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Nijinsky, Romola (Box 1)
    - Page, Ruth and Tom Fisher (Box 1)
    - Reinhardt, Max (Box 1)
    - San Francisco Museum of Art (Box 1)
    - Stokowski, Leopold (Box 1)
    - Stravinsky, Igor (Box 1)
    - Sweden, Consulate (Box 1)
    - Walter, Bruno (Box 1)
    - "Lottie" (Box 1)
    - Letter of Condolence, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Postcards and greetings cards, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Telegrams (Box 1)
    - Unidentified miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, outgoing (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, business (Box 1)
  - Legal / business
    - Contracts, 1932-1949; undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1950; undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Address books (Box 2)
  - Books, 11 items (Box 6)
  - Engagement calendar, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper mats, card case, bank book (Box 2)
  - Painting (Box 2)
  - Scheherezade Ballet (cast), 1935 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1: Miscellaneous (Oversize 1)
    - 2: Theater reviews, programs (Oversize 1)
    - 3: Clippings (Oversize 1)
    - 4: Music (Oversize 1)
    - 5: Oversize photographs (Oversize 1)
  - "White Peacock" (piano roll), 1935; played by Charles Griffes for A.B., 10 Jun 1920 (notes: OK on Steinway Concert Grand, OK on Weber with concert grand adjustment) (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Adolf Bolm Ballet
    - "Ballet McCarnigul" (Box 2)
    - "Russian peasant dance" (Box 2)
    - "Scheherezade" (Box 2)
    - "Spring dance" (Box 2)
    - "Spring dance" (Box 2)
    - "Streuss valse" (Box 2)
  - "Bal de Marionettes" (Box 2)
  - Ballet Intime
    - Group portraits, 1911 (Box 2)
    - "Apollon musagetes" (Box 2)
    - "Assyrian Dance" (Box 2)
    - "Caucasian mountain dance" (Box 2)
    - "Greek dance" (Box 2)
    - "Harlequinade" (Box 2)
    - "Javanese dance" (Box 2)
    - "Legend" (Box 2)
    - "Mazurka" (Box 2)
    - "Mexican episode" (Box 2)
    - "Nymph and Fawn" (Box 2)
    - "Roman dance" (Box 2)
    - "Spanish rhythm" (Box 2)
    - Suggestions diabolique" (Box 2)
    - "Tragedy of the cello" (Box 2)
    - "Visions fugitives" (Box 2)
  - Bolm, Adolf (portraits) (Box 2)
  - Bolm dancers at the Hollywood Bowl (Box 2)
  - Bolm dancers at the Hollywood Bowl - "Reverie" (Box 2)
  - Chicago Civic Opera
    - Julia Barashkura (Box 3)
    - "Lakme" (Bolmas Siva) (Box 3)
  - Chicago Grand Opera Company
    - "Birthday of the Infanta" (Box 3)
  - Cornish School, Seattle, 1921
  - Diaghilev Ballet
    - "Carnival" (Box 3)
    - "Firebird" (Box 3)
    - "Le Pavillon d'Armide" (Box 3)
    - "Petrouchka" (Box 3)
    - "Les Sylphides" (Box 3)
    - "Tamar" (Box 3)
  - "Hunchback of Notre Dame" (Box 3)
  - Inscribed photographs (to A.B.) (Box 3)
  - Karsavina, Thamar (Box 3)
  - "Mechanical ballet" (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Grand Opera Co.
    - "Coq d'Or" (Box 3)
    - "Coq d'Or" (glassplate) (Box 3)
  - Misc - family
    - Misc - negatives (Box 3)
    - Misc - individuals, unidentified (Box 3)
    - Misc - group portraits, unidentified (Box 3)
    - Misc - glassplate, costume (Box 3)
  - Modern Composer's Group - "Krazy Kat" (Box 3)
  - "Mozart" (Box 3)
  - Page, Ruth (Box 3)
  - "Parnassian Chicagoans" A.D. 2000 (Box 3)
  - "Petrouchka, Mandragore" (Box 3)
  - "Prince Igor" (Box 3)
  - "Russian dance" (Box 3)
  - "Samson" (Box 3)
  - San Francisco Opera Co.
    - "Coq d'Or" (Box 3)
  - Stage sets (Box 4)
  - Ziegfeld, "Falling Leaves" (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - Adolf Bolm School of Dance (Box 4)
  - Art exhibitions (Box 4)
  - About A.B., 3 folders (Box 4)
  - By A.B., 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Book (Japanese) (Box 4)
  - Choreography (Box 4)
  - Dance programs, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Misc dance (Box 5)
  - Misc dance people (Box 5)
  - Hollywood Civil Ballet Company (Box 5)
  - Itineraries (Box 5)
  - Music, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Musical events (Box 5)
  - Plays (Box 5)
  - Press releases (Box 5)
  - Radio interviews (Box 5)
- Writings
  - By Bolm (Box 5)
  - By Bolm, notes (Box 5)
  - Author unidentified (Box 5)